{
  "chapter_name": "PERMUTATIONS AND COMBINATIONS",
  "chapter_text": "Suppose you have a suitcase with a number lock. The number lock has 4 wheels each labelled with 10 digits from 0 to 9. The lock can be opened if 4 specific digits are arranged in a particular sequence with no repetition. Some how, you have forgotten this specific sequence of digits. You remember only the first digit which is 7. In order to open the lock, how many sequences of 3-digits you may have to check with? To answer this question, you may, immediately, start listing all possible arrangements of 9 remaining digits taken 3 at a time. But, this method will be tedious, because the number of possible sequences may be large. Here, in this Chapter, we shall learn some basic counting techniques which will enable us to answer this question without actually listing 3-digit arrangements. In fact, these techniques will be useful in determining the number of different ways of arranging and selecting objects without actually listing them. As a first step, we shall examine a principle which is most fundamental to the learning of these techniques.\n\nLet us consider the following problem. Mohan has 3 pants and 2 shirts. How many different pairs of a pant and a shirt, can he dress up with? There are 3 ways in which a pant can be chosen, because there are 3 pants available. Similarly, a shirt can be chosen in 2 ways. For every choice of a pant, there are 2 choices of a shirt. Therefore, there are 3 × 2 = 6 pairs of a pant and a shirt.\n\nIn fact, the problems of the above types are solved by applying the following principle known as the fundamental principle of counting, or, simply, the multiplication principle, which states that\n\n'If an event can occur in m different ways, following which another event can occur in n different ways, then the total number of occurrence of the events in the given order is m×n.'\n\nThe above principle can be generalised for any finite number of events. For example, for 3 events, the principle is as follows:\n\n'If an event can occur in m different ways, following which another event can occur in n different ways, following which a third event can occur in p different ways, then the total number of occurrence to 'the events in the given order is m × n × p.'\n\nIn the first problem, the required number of ways of wearing a pant and a shirt was the number of different ways of the occurence of the following events in succession:\n\n(i) the event of choosing a pant\n(ii) the event of choosing a shirt.\n\nIn the second problem, the required number of ways was the number of different ways of the occurence of the following events in succession:\n\n(i) the event of choosing a school bag\n(ii) the event of choosing a tiffin box\n(iii) the event of choosing a water bottle.\n\nHere, in both the cases, the events in each problem could occur in various possible orders. But, we have to choose any one of the possible orders and count the number of different ways of the occurence of the events in this chosen order.\n\nIn Example 1 of the previous Section, we are actually counting the different possible arrangements of the letters such as ROSE, REOS, ..., etc. Here, in this list, each arrangement is different from other. In other words, the order of writing the letters is important. Each arrangement is called a permutation of 4 different letters taken all at a time. Now, if we have to determine the number of 3-letter words, with or without meaning, which can be formed out of the letters of the word NUMBER, where the repetition of the letters is not allowed, we need to count the arrangements NUM, NMU, MUN, NUB, ..., etc. Here, we are counting the permutations of 6 different letters taken 3 at a time. The required number of words = 6 × 5 × 4 = 120 (by using multiplication principle).\n\nIf the repetition of the letters was allowed, the required number of words would be 6 × 6 × 6 = 216.\n\nLet us now go back to the stage where we had determined the following formula:\n\n$$^nP_r = n (n – 1) (n – 2) . . . (n – r + 1)$$\n\nMultiplying numerator and denominator by $(n – r)(n – r – 1) . . . 3 × 2 × 1$, we get\n\n$$^nP_r = \\frac{n(n-1)(n-2)...(n-r+1)(n-r)(n-r-1)...3 × 2 × 1}{(n-r)(n-r-1)...3 × 2 × 1} = \\frac{n!}{(n-r)!},$$\n\nThus\n\n$$^nP_r = \\frac{n!}{(n-r)!}, \\text{where } 0 < r \\leq n$$\n\nThis is a much more convenient expression for $^nP_r$ than the previous one.\n\nIn particular, when $r = n$, $^nP_n = \\frac{n!}{0!} = n!$\n\nCounting permutations is merely counting the number of ways in which some or all objects at a time are rearranged. Arranging no object at all is the same as leaving behind all the objects and we know that there is only one way of doing so. Thus, we can have\n\n$$^nP_0 = 1 = \\frac{n!}{n!} = \\frac{n!}{(n-0)!} \\quad ... (1)$$\n\nTherefore, the formula (1) is applicable for $r = 0$ also.\n\nThus\n\n$$^nP_r = \\frac{n!}{(n-r)!}, 0 \\leq r \\leq n .$$\n\nThe number of permutations of n different objects taken r at a time, where repetition is allowed, is n^r.\n\nSuppose we have to find the number of ways of rearranging the letters of the word ROOT. In this case, the letters of the word are not all different. There are 2 Os, which are of the same kind. Let us treat, temporarily, the 2 Os as different, say, O₁ and O₂. The number of permutations of 4-different letters, in this case, taken all at a time is 4!. Consider one of these permutations say, RO₁O₂T. Corresponding to this permutation, we have 2! permutations RO₁O₂T and RO₂O₁T which will be exactly the same permutation if O₁ and O₂ are not treated as different, i.e., if O₁ and O₂ are the same O at both places.\n\nTherefore, the required number of permutations = 4!/2! = 3×4 = 12.\n\nWe can state (without proof) the following theorems:\n\n### Theorem 3 \nThe number of permutations of n objects, where p objects are of the same kind and rest are all different = \n\n$$\\frac{n!}{p!}$$\n\nIn fact, we have a more general theorem.\n\n### Theorem 4 \nThe number of permutations of n objects, where p₁ objects are of one kind, p₂ are of second kind, ..., pₖ are of kᵗʰ kind and the rest, if any, are of different kind is \n\n$$\\frac{n!}{p₁!p₂!...p_k!}$$\n\nLet us now assume that there is a group of 3 lawn tennis players X, Y, Z. A team consisting of 2 players is to be formed. In how many ways can we do so? Is the team of X and Y different from the team of Y and X ? Here, order is not important. In fact, there are only 3 possible ways in which the team could be constructed.\n\nThese examples suggest the following theorem showing relationship between permutation and combination:\n\n**Theorem 5** $$^nP_r = ^nC_r \\cdot r!, 0 < r \\leq n.$$\n\n**Proof** Corresponding to each combination of $$^nC_r$$, we have r ! permutations, because r objects in every combination can be rearranged in r ! ways.\n\nHence, the total number of permutations of n different things taken r at a time is $$^nC_r \\times r!$$. On the other hand, it is $$^nP_r$$. Thus\n\n$$^nP_r = ^nC_r \\times r!, 0 < r \\leq n.$$\n\n**Remarks** 1. From above $$\\frac{n!}{(n-r)!} = ^nC_r \\times r!$$, i.e., $$^nC_r = \\frac{n!}{r!(n-r)!}.$$\n\nIn particular, if r = n , $$^nC_n = \\frac{n!}{n! 0!} = 1.$$\n\n2. We define $$^nC_0 = 1$$, i.e., the number of combinations of n different things taken nothing at all is considered to be 1. Counting combinations is merely counting the number of ways in which some or all objects at a time are selected. Selecting nothing at all is the same as leaving behind all the objects and we know that there is only one way of doing so. This way we define $$^nC_0 = 1$$.\n\n3. As $$\\frac{n!}{0!(n-0)!} = 1 = ^nC_0$$, the formula $$^nC_r = \\frac{n!}{r!(n-r)!}$$ is applicable for r = 0 also.\n\nHence\n\n$$^nC_r = \\frac{n!}{r!(n-r)!}, 0 \\leq r \\leq n.$$\n\n4. $$^nC_{n-r} = \\frac{n!}{(n-r)![n-(n-r)]!} = \\frac{n!}{(n-r)!r!} = ^nC_r,$$\n\ni.e., selecting r objects out of n objects is same as rejecting (n - r) objects.\n\n5. $$^nC_a = ^nC_b \\Rightarrow a = b$$ or $$a = n - b$$, i.e., $$n = a + b$$\n\nTheorem 6 $$^nC_r + ^nC_{r-1} = ^{n+1}C_r$$\n\nProof We have \n\n$$^nC_r + ^nC_{r-1} = \\frac{n!}{r!(n-r)!} + \\frac{n!}{(r-1)!(n-r+1)!}$$\n\n$$= \\frac{n!}{r \\times (r-1)!(n-r)!} + \\frac{n!}{(r-1)!(n-r+1)(n-r)!}$$\n\n$$= \\frac{n!}{(r-1)!(n-r)!} \\left[\\frac{1}{r} + \\frac{1}{n-r+1}\\right]$$\n\n$$= \\frac{n!}{(r-1)!(n-r)!} \\times \\frac{n-r+1+r}{r(n-r+1)} = \\frac{(n+1)!}{r!(n+1-r)!} = ^{n+1}C_r$$",
  "example_problems": [
    {
      "question": "Find the number of 4 letter words, with or without meaning, which can be formed out of the letters of the word ROSE, where the repetition of the letters is not allowed.",
      "reasoning": "There are as many words as there are ways of filling in 4 vacant places by the 4 letters, keeping in mind that the repetition is not allowed. The first place can be filled in 4 different ways by anyone of the 4 letters R,O,S,E. Following which, the second place can be filled in by anyone of the remaining 3 letters in 3 different ways, following which the third place can be filled in 2 different ways; following which, the fourth place can be filled in 1 way. Thus, the number of ways in which the 4 places can be filled, by the multiplication principle, is 4 × 3 × 2 × 1 = 24. Hence, the required number of words is 24.",
      "answer": "24"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given 4 flags of different colours, how many different signals can be generated, if a signal requires the use of 2 flags one below the other?",
      "reasoning": "There will be as many signals as there are ways of filling in 2 vacant places in succession by the 4 flags of different colours. The upper vacant place can be filled in 4 different ways by anyone of the 4 flags; following which, the lower vacant place can be filled in 3 different ways by anyone of the remaining 3 different flags. Hence, by the multiplication principle, the required number of signals = 4 × 3 = 12.",
      "answer": "12"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many 2 digit even numbers can be formed from the digits 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 if the digits can be repeated?",
      "reasoning": "There will be as many ways as there are ways of filling 2 vacant places in succession by the five given digits. Here, in this case, we start filling in unit's place, because the options for this place are 2 and 4 only and this can be done in 2 ways; following which the ten's place can be filled by any of the 5 digits in 5 different ways as the digits can be repeated. Therefore, by the multiplication principle, the required number of two digits even numbers is 2 × 5, i.e., 10.",
      "answer": "10"
    },
    {
      "question": "Find the number of different signals that can be generated by arranging at least 2 flags in order (one below the other) on a vertical staff, if five different flags are available.",
      "reasoning": "A signal can consist of either 2 flags, 3 flags, 4 flags or 5 flags. Now, let us count the possible number of signals consisting of 2 flags, 3 flags, 4 flags and 5 flags separately and then add the respective numbers.\n\nThere will be as many 2 flag signals as there are ways of filling in 2 vacant places in succession by the 5 flags available. By Multiplication rule, the number of ways is 5 × 4 = 20.\n\nSimilarly, there will be as many 3 flag signals as there are ways of filling in 3 vacant places in succession by the 5 flags.\n\nThe number of ways is 5 × 4 × 3 = 60.\nContinuing the same way, we find that\nThe number of 4 flag signals = 5 × 4 × 3 × 2 = 120\nand        the number of 5 flag signals = 5 × 4 × 3 × 2 × 1 = 120\nTherefore,   the required no of signals = 20 + 60 + 120 + 120 = 320.",
      "answer": "320"
    },
    {
      "question": "Evaluate (i) 5 !    (ii) 7 !     (iii) 7 ! – 5!",
      "reasoning": "(i) 5 ! = 1 × 2 × 3 × 4 × 5 = 120\n(ii) 7 ! = 1 × 2 × 3 × 4 × 5 × 6 ×7 = 5040\nand (iii) 7 ! – 5! = 5040 – 120 = 4920.",
      "answer": "(i) 120 (ii) 5040 (iii) 4920"
    },
    {
      "question": "Compute (i) $\\frac{7!}{5!}$     (ii) $\\frac{12!}{(10!)(2!)}$",
      "reasoning": "(i) We have $\\frac{7!}{5!} = \\frac{7 \\times 6 \\times 5!}{5!} = 7 \\times 6 = 42$\n\nand        \n(ii) $\\frac{12!}{(10!)(2!)} = \\frac{12 \\times 11 \\times (10!)}{(10!) \\times (2)} = 6 \\times 11 = 66.$",
      "answer": "(i) 42 (ii) 66"
    },
    {
      "question": "Evaluate $\\frac{n!}{r!(n-r)!}$, when n = 5, r = 2.",
      "reasoning": "We have to evaluate $\\frac{5!}{2!(5-2)!}$ (since n = 5, r = 2)\n\nWe have $\\frac{5!}{2!(5-2)!} = \\frac{5!}{2! \\times 3!} = \\frac{5 \\times 4}{2} = 10$.",
      "answer": "10"
    },
    {
      "question": "If $\\frac{1}{8!} + \\frac{1}{9!} = \\frac{x}{10!}$, find x.",
      "reasoning": "We have $\\frac{1}{8!} + \\frac{1}{9 \\times 8!} = \\frac{x}{10 \\times 9 \\times 8!}$\n\nTherefore $1 + \\frac{1}{9} = \\frac{x}{10 \\times 9}$ or $\\frac{10}{9} = \\frac{x}{10 \\times 9}$\n\nSo x = 100.",
      "answer": "100"
    },
    {
      "question": "Find the number of permutations of the letters of the word ALLAHABAD.",
      "reasoning": "Here, there are 9 objects (letters) of which there are 4A's, 2 L's and rest are all different.\n\nTherefore, the required number of arrangements = \n\n$$\\frac{9!}{4!2!} = \\frac{5 \\times 6 \\times 7 \\times 8 \\times 9}{2} = 7560$$.",
      "answer": "7560"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many 4-digit numbers can be formed by using the digits 1 to 9 if repetition of digits is not allowed?",
      "reasoning": "Here order matters for example 1234 and 1324 are two different numbers. Therefore, there will be as many 4 digit numbers as there are permutations of 9 different digits taken 4 at a time.\n\nTherefore, the required 4 digit numbers = ₉P₄ = $\\frac{9!}{(9-4)!} = \\frac{9!}{5!} = 9 \\times 8 \\times 7 \\times 6 = 3024$.",
      "answer": "3024"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many numbers lying between 100 and 1000 can be formed with the digits 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, if the repetition of the digits is not allowed?",
      "reasoning": "Every number between 100 and 1000 is a 3-digit number. We, first, have to count the permutations of 6 digits taken 3 at a time. This number would be ⁶P₃. But, these permutations will include those also where 0 is at the 100's place. For example, 092, 042, . . ., etc are such numbers which are actually 2-digit numbers and hence the number of such numbers has to be subtracted from ⁶P₃ to get the required number. To get the number of such numbers, we fix 0 at the 100's place and rearrange the remaining 5 digits taking 2 at a time. This number is ⁵P₂. So\n\nThe required number = ⁶P₃ − ⁵P₂ = 6! − 5!\n                                  3!   3!\n                    = 4 × 5 × 6 – 4 ×5 = 100",
      "answer": "100"
    },
    {
      "question": "Find the value of n such that (i) ⁿP₅ = 42 ⁿP₃, n > 4        (ii) ⁿP₄ / ⁿ⁻¹P₄ = 5/3, n > 4",
      "reasoning": "(i) Given that ⁿP₅ = 42 ⁿP₃\n\nor n (n – 1) (n – 2) (n – 3) (n – 4) = 42 n(n – 1) (n – 2)\n\nSince n > 4      so n(n – 1) (n – 2) ≠ 0\n\nTherefore, by dividing both sides by n(n – 1) (n – 2), we get\n(n – 3 (n – 4) = 42\n\nor n² – 7n – 30 = 0\n\nor n² – 10n + 3n – 30\n\nor (n – 10) (n + 3) = 0\n\nor n – 10 = 0 or  n + 3 = 0\n\nor n = 10     or  n = – 3\n\nAs n cannot be negative, so n = 10.\n\n(ii) Given that ⁿP₄ / ⁿ⁻¹P₄ = 5/3\n\nTherefore 3n (n – 1) (n – 2) (n – 3) = 5(n – 1) (n – 2) (n – 3) (n – 4)\n\nor 3n = 5 (n – 4)    [as (n – 1) (n – 2) (n – 3) ≠ 0, n > 4]\n\nor n = 10.",
      "answer": "(i) 10 (ii) 10"
    },
    {
      "question": "Find r, if 5 ⁴Pᵣ = 6 ⁵Pᵣ₋₁.",
      "reasoning": "We have 5 ⁴Pᵣ = 6 ⁵Pᵣ₋₁\n\nor           5 × 4! / (4 - r)! = 6 × 5! / (5 - r + 1)!\n\nor           5! / (4 - r)! = 6 × 5! / [(5 - r + 1)(5 - r)(5 - r - 1)!]\n\nor           (6 - r)(5 - r) = 6\nor           r² - 11r + 24 = 0\nor           r² - 8r - 3r + 24 = 0\nor           (r - 8)(r - 3) = 0\nor           r = 8 or r = 3.\nHence        r = 8, 3.",
      "answer": "8, 3"
    },
    {
      "question": "Find the number of different 8-letter arrangements that can be made from the letters of the word DAUGHTER so that (i) all vowels occur together (ii) all vowels do not occur together.",
      "reasoning": "(i) There are 8 different letters in the word DAUGHTER, in which there are 3 vowels, namely, A, U and E. Since the vowels have to occur together, we can for the time being, assume them as a single object (AUE). This single object together with 5 remaining letters (objects) will be counted as 6 objects. Then we count permutations of these 6 objects taken all at a time. This number would be ⁶P₆ = 6!. Corresponding to each of these permutations, we shall have 3! permutations of the three vowels A, U, E taken all at a time. Hence, by the multiplication principle the required number of permutations = 6! × 3! = 4320.\n\n(ii) If we have to count those permutations in which all vowels are never together, we first have to find all possible arrangements of 8 letters taken all at a time, which can be done in 8! ways. Then, we have to subtract from this number, the number of permutations in which the vowels are always together.\n\nTherefore, the required number \n8! - 6! × 3! = 6!(7×8 - 6)\n            = 2 × 6!(28 - 3)\n            = 50 × 6! = 50 × 720 = 36000",
      "answer": "(i) 4320 (ii) 36000"
    },
    {
      "question": "In how many ways can 4 red, 3 yellow and 2 green discs be arranged in a row if the discs of the same colour are indistinguishable?",
      "reasoning": "Total number of discs are 4 + 3 + 2 = 9. Out of 9 discs, 4 are of the first kind (red), 3 are of the second kind (yellow) and 2 are of the third kind (green).\n\nTherefore, the number of arrangements $\\frac{9!}{4! 3! 2!} = 1260$.",
      "answer": "1260"
    },
    {
      "question": "Find the number of arrangements of the letters of the word INDEPENDENCE. In how many of these arrangements, (i) do the words start with P (ii) do all the vowels always occur together (iii) do the vowels never occur together (iv) do the words begin with I and end in P?",
      "reasoning": "There are 12 letters, of which N appears 3 times, E appears 4 times and D appears 2 times and the rest are all different. Therefore\n\nThe required number of arrangements = $\\frac{12!}{3! 4! 2!} = 1663200$\n\n(i) Let us fix P at the extreme left position, we, then, count the arrangements of the remaining 11 letters. Therefore, the required number of words starting with P\n\n   = $\\frac{11!}{3! 2! 4!} = 138600$\n\n(ii) There are 5 vowels in the given word, which are 4 Es and 1 I. Since, they have to always occur together, we treat them as a single object EEEEI for the time being. This single object together with 7 remaining objects will account for 8 objects. These 8 objects, in which there are 3Ns and 2 Ds, can be rearranged in\n\n   $\\frac{8!}{3! 2!}$ ways. Corresponding to each of these arrangements, the 5 vowels E, E, E, E and I can be rearranged in $\\frac{5!}{4!}$ ways. Therefore, by multiplication principle, the required number of arrangements\n\n   = $\\frac{8!}{3! 2!} \\times \\frac{5!}{4!} = 16800$\n\n(iii) The required number of arrangements\n     = the total number of arrangements (without any restriction) – the number\n       of arrangements where all the vowels occur together.\n\n= 1663200 – 16800 = 1646400\n(iv)   Let us fix I and P at the extreme ends (I at the left end and P at the right end).\n       We are left with 10 letters.\n       Hence, the required number of arrangements\n\n       $$= \\frac{10!}{3! 2! 4!} = 12600$$",
      "answer": "(i) 138600 (ii) 16800 (iii) 1646400 (iv) 12600"
    },
    {
      "question": "If $$^nC_9 = ^nC_8$$, find $$^nC_{17}$$.",
      "reasoning": "We have $$^nC_9 = ^nC_8$$\n\ni.e., \n\n$$\\frac{n!}{9!(n-9)!} = \\frac{n!}{(n-8)!8!}$$\n\nor\n\n$$\\frac{1}{9} = \\frac{1}{n-8}$$ or $$n - 8 = 9$$ or $$n = 17$$\n\nTherefore $$^nC_{17} = ^{17}C_{17} = 1$$.",
      "answer": "1"
    },
    {
      "question": "A committee of 3 persons is to be constituted from a group of 2 men and 3 women. In how many ways can this be done? How many of these committees would consist of 1 man and 2 women?",
      "reasoning": "Here, order does not matter. Therefore, we need to count combinations. There will be as many committees as there are combinations of 5 different persons taken 3 at a time. Hence, the required number of ways = $$^5C_3 = \\frac{5!}{3!2!} = \\frac{4 \\times 5}{2} = 10$$.\n\nNow, 1 man can be selected from 2 men in $$^2C_1$$ ways and 2 women can be selected from 3 women in $$^3C_2$$ ways. Therefore, the required number of committees\n\n$$= ^2C_1 \\times ^3C_2 = \\frac{2!}{1! 1!} \\times \\frac{3!}{2! 1!} = 6.$$",
      "answer": "10; 6"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the number of ways of choosing 4 cards from a pack of 52 playing cards? In how many of these (i) four cards are of the same suit, (ii) four cards belong to four different suits, (iii) are face cards, (iv) two are red cards and two are black cards, (v) cards are of the same colour?",
      "reasoning": "There will be as many ways of choosing 4 cards from 52 cards as there are combinations of 52 different things, taken 4 at a time. Therefore\n\nThe required number of ways = $^{52}C_4 = \\frac{52!}{4! 48!} = \\frac{49 \\times 50 \\times 51 \\times 52}{2 \\times 3 \\times 4} = 270725$\n\n(i) There are four suits: diamond, club, spade, heart and there are 13 cards of each suit. Therefore, there are $^{13}C_4$ ways of choosing 4 diamonds. Similarly, there are $^{13}C_4$ ways of choosing 4 clubs, $^{13}C_4$ ways of choosing 4 spades and $^{13}C_4$ ways of choosing 4 hearts. Therefore\n   The required number of ways = $^{13}C_4 + ^{13}C_4 + ^{13}C_4 + ^{13}C_4$.\n\n   $$= 4 \\times \\frac{13!}{4! 9!} = 2860$$\n\n(ii) There are13 cards in each suit.\n    Therefore, there are $^{13}C_1$ ways of choosing 1 card from 13 cards of diamond, $^{13}C_1$ ways of choosing 1 card from 13 cards of hearts, $^{13}C_1$ ways of choosing 1 card from 13 cards of clubs, $^{13}C_1$ ways of choosing 1 card from 13 cards of spades. Hence, by multiplication principle, the required number of ways\n    $$= ^{13}C_1 \\times ^{13}C_1 \\times ^{13}C_1 \\times ^{13}C_1 = 13^4$$\n\n(iii) There are 12 face cards and 4 are to be selected out of these 12 cards. This can be\n\n     done in $^{12}C_4$ ways. Therefore, the required number of ways = $\\frac{12!}{4! 8!} = 495$.\n\n(iv) There are 26 red cards and 26 black cards. Therefore, the required number of\n     ways = ²⁶C₂ × ²⁶C₂\n\n     $$ = \\left(\\frac{26!}{2! 24!}\\right)^2 = (325)^2 = 105625 $$\n\n(v) 4 red cards can be selected out of 26 red cards in ²⁶C₄ ways.\n    4 black cards can be selected out of 26 black cards in ²⁶C₄ways.\nTherefore, the required number of ways = ²⁶C₄ + ²⁶C₄\n\n     $$ = 2 \\times \\frac{26!}{4! 22!} = 29900. $$",
      "answer": "(i)270725 (ii)2860 (iii)28561 (iv)495 (v)105625 (vi)29900"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many words, with or without meaning, each of 3 vowels and 2 consonants can be formed from the letters of the word INVOLUTE?",
      "reasoning": "In the word INVOLUTE, there are 4 vowels, namely, I,O,E,U and 4 consonants, namely, N, V, L and T.\nThe number of ways of selecting 3 vowels out of 4 = ⁴C₃ = 4.\nThe number of ways of selecting 2 consonants out of 4 = ⁴C₂ = 6.\n\nTherefore, the number of combinations of 3 vowels and 2 consonants is 4 × 6 = 24.\n\nNow, each of these 24 combinations has 5 letters which can be arranged among themselves in 5! ways. Therefore, the required number of different words is 24 × 5! = 2880.",
      "answer": "2880"
    },
    {
      "question": "A group consists of 4 girls and 7 boys. In how many ways can a team of 5 members be selected if the team has (i) no girl? (ii) at least one boy and one girl? (iii) at least 3 girls?",
      "reasoning": "(i) Since, the team will not include any girl, therefore, only boys are to be selected. 5 boys out of 7 boys can be selected in ⁷C₅ ways. Therefore, the required number of ways\n\n   = ⁷C₅ = 7! / (5! 2!) = (6 × 7) / 2 = 21\n\n(ii) Since, at least one boy and one girl are to be there in every team. Therefore, the team can consist of\n   (a) 1 boy and 4 girls\n   (b) 2 boys and 3 girls\n   (c) 3 boys and 2 girls\n   (d) 4 boys and 1 girl.\n\n   1 boy and 4 girls can be selected in ⁷C₁ × ⁴C₄ ways.\n   2 boys and 3 girls can be selected in ⁷C₂ × ⁴C₃ ways.\n   3 boys and 2 girls can be selected in ⁷C₃ × ⁴C₂ ways.\n   4 boys and 1 girl can be selected in ⁷C₄ × ⁴C₁ ways.\n\n   Therefore, the required number of ways\n   = ⁷C₁ × ⁴C₄ + ⁷C₂ × ⁴C₃ + ⁷C₃ × ⁴C₂ + ⁷C₄ × ⁴C₁\n   = 7 + 84 + 210 + 140 = 441\n\n(iii) Since, the team has to consist of at least 3 girls, the team can consist of\n   (a) 3 girls and 2 boys, or\n   (b) 4 girls and 1 boy.\n\nNote that the team cannot have all 5 girls, because, the group has only 4 girls.\n\n3 girls and 2 boys can be selected in ⁴C₃ × ⁷C₂ ways.\n4 girls and 1 boy can be selected in ⁴C₄ × ⁷C₁ ways.\n\nTherefore, the required number of ways\n= ⁴C₃ × ⁷C₂ + ⁴C₄ × ⁷C₁ = 84 + 7 = 91",
      "answer": "(i) 21 (ii) 441 (iii) 91"
    },
    {
      "question": "Find the number of words with or without meaning which can be made using all the letters of the word AGAIN. If these words are written as in a dictionary, what will be the 50th word?",
      "reasoning": "There are 5 letters in the word AGAIN, in which A appears 2 times. Therefore,\n\nthe required number of words = $$\\frac{5!}{2!} = 60$$.\n\nTo get the number of words starting with A, we fix the letter A at the extreme left position, we then rearrange the remaining 4 letters taken all at a time. There will be as many arrangements of these 4 letters taken 4 at a time as there are permutations of 4 different things taken 4 at a time. Hence, the number of words starting with\n\nA = 4! = 24. Then, starting with G, the number of words = $$\\frac{4!}{2!} = 12$$ as after placing G at the extreme left position, we are left with the letters A, A, I and N. Similarly, there are 12 words starting with the next letter I. Total number of words so far obtained = 24 + 12 + 12 = 48.\n\nThe 49th word is NAAGI. The 50th word is NAAIG.",
      "answer": "60, NAAIG"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many numbers greater than 1000000 can be formed by using the digits 1, 2, 0, 2, 4, 2, 4?",
      "reasoning": "Since, 1000000 is a 7-digit number and the number of digits to be used is also 7. Therefore, the numbers to be counted will be 7-digit only. Also, the numbers have to be greater than 1000000, so they can begin either with 1, 2 or 4.\n\nThe number of numbers beginning with 1 = $\\frac{6!}{3! 2!} = \\frac{4 \\times 5 \\times 6}{2} = 60$, as when 1 is fixed at the extreme left position, the remaining digits to be rearranged will be 0, 2, 2, 2, 4, 4, in which there are 3, 2s and 2, 4s.\n\nTotal numbers beginning with 2\n\n= $\\frac{6!}{2! 2!} = \\frac{3 \\times 4 \\times 5 \\times 6}{2} = 180$\n\nand total numbers beginning with 4 = $\\frac{6!}{3!} = 4 \\times 5 \\times 6 = 120$\n\nTherefore, the required number of numbers = 60 + 180 + 120 = 360.",
      "answer": "360"
    },
    {
      "question": "In how many ways can 5 girls and 3 boys be seated in a row so that no two boys are together?",
      "reasoning": "Let us first seat the 5 girls. This can be done in 5! ways. For each such arrangement, the three boys can be seated only at the cross marked places.\n× G × G × G × G × G ×.\nThere are 6 cross marked places and the three boys can be seated in $$^6P_3$$ ways. Hence, by multiplication principle, the total number of ways\n\n= 5! × $$^6P_3$$ = 5! × $$\\frac{6!}{3!}$$\n= 4 × 5 × 2 × 3 × 4 × 5 × 6 = 14400.",
      "answer": "14400"
    }
  ],
  "exercises": [
    {
      "question": "How many 3-digit numbers can be formed from the digits 1, 2, 3, 4 and 5 assuming that (i) repetition of the digits is allowed? (ii) repetition of the digits is not allowed?",
      "answer": "(i) 125 (ii) 60"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many 3-digit even numbers can be formed from the digits 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 if the digits can be repeated?",
      "answer": "108"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many 4-letter code can be formed using the first 10 letters of the English alphabet, if no letter can be repeated?",
      "answer": "5040"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many 5-digit telephone numbers can be constructed using the digits 0 to 9 if each number starts with 67 and no digit appears more than once?",
      "answer": "336"
    },
    {
      "question": "A coin is tossed 3 times and the outcomes are recorded. How many possible outcomes are there?",
      "answer": "8"
    },
    {
      "question": "Given 5 flags of different colours, how many different signals can be generated if each signal requires the use of 2 flags, one below the other?",
      "answer": "20"
    },
    {
      "question": "Evaluate (i) 8 ! (ii) 4 ! – 3 !",
      "answer": "(i) 40320 (ii) 183"
    },
    {
      "question": "Is 3 ! + 4 ! = 7 ! ?",
      "answer": "No; 30."
    },
    {
      "question": "Compute $\\frac{8!}{6! \\times 2!}$",
      "answer": "28"
    },
    {
      "question": "If $\\frac{1}{6!} + \\frac{1}{7!} = \\frac{x}{8!}$, find x",
      "answer": "64"
    },
    {
      "question": "Evaluate $\\frac{n!}{(n-r)!}$, when (i) n = 6, r = 2 (ii) n = 9, r = 5.",
      "answer": "(i) 30 (ii) 15120"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many 3-digit numbers can be formed by using the digits 1 to 9 if no digit is repeated?",
      "answer": "504"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many 4-digit numbers are there with no digit repeated?",
      "answer": "4536"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many 3-digit even numbers can be made using the digits 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 7, if no digit is repeated?",
      "answer": "60"
    },
    {
      "question": "Find the number of 4-digit numbers that can be formed using the digits 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 if no digit is repeated. How many of these will be even?",
      "answer": "120, 48"
    },
    {
      "question": "From a committee of 8 persons, in how many ways can we choose a chairman and a vice chairman assuming one person can not hold more than one position?",
      "answer": "56"
    },
    {
      "question": "Find n if $$_{n-1}P_3 : _nP_4 = 1 : 9$$.",
      "answer": "9"
    },
    {
      "question": "Find r if (i) $$_5P_r = _6P_{r-1}$$ (ii) $$_5P_r = _6P_{r-1}$$.",
      "answer": "(i) 3 (ii) 4"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many words, with or without meaning, can be formed using all the letters of the word EQUATION, using each letter exactly once?",
      "answer": "40320"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many words, with or without meaning can be made from the letters of the word MONDAY, assuming that no letter is repeated, if: (i) 4 letters are used at a time, (ii) all letters are used at a time, (iii) all letters are used but first letter is a vowel?",
      "answer": "(i) 360 (ii) 720 (iii) 240"
    },
    {
      "question": "In how many of the distinct permutations of the letters in MISSISSIPPI do the four I's not come together?",
      "answer": "33810"
    },
    {
      "question": "In how many ways can the letters of the word PERMUTATIONS be arranged if the (i) words start with P and end with S, (ii) vowels are all together, (iii) there are always 4 letters between P and S?",
      "answer": "(i) 1814400 (ii) 2419200 (iii) 25401600"
    },
    {
      "question": "If ⁿC₈ = ⁿC₂, find ⁿC₂.",
      "answer": "45"
    },
    {
      "question": "Determine n if (i) ²ⁿC₃ : ⁿC₃ = 12 : 1 (ii) ²ⁿC₃ : ⁿC₃ = 11 : 1",
      "answer": "(i) 5 (ii) 6"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many chords can be drawn through 21 points on a circle?",
      "answer": "210"
    },
    {
      "question": "In how many ways can a team of 3 boys and 3 girls be selected from 5 boys and 4 girls?",
      "answer": "40"
    },
    {
      "question": "Find the number of ways of selecting 9 balls from 6 red balls, 5 white balls and 5 blue balls if each selection consists of 3 balls of each colour.",
      "answer": "2000"
    },
    {
      "question": "Determine the number of 5 card combinations out of a deck of 52 cards if there is exactly one ace in each combination.",
      "answer": "778320"
    },
    {
      "question": "In how many ways can one select a cricket team of eleven from 17 players in which only 5 players can bowl if each cricket team of 11 must include exactly 4 bowlers?",
      "answer": "3960"
    },
    {
      "question": "A bag contains 5 black and 6 red balls. Determine the number of ways in which 2 black and 3 red balls can be selected.",
      "answer": "200"
    },
    {
      "question": "In how many ways can a student choose a programme of 5 courses if 9 courses are available and 2 specific courses are compulsory for every student?",
      "answer": "35"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many words, with or without meaning, each of 2 vowels and 3 consonants can be formed from the letters of the word DAUGHTER ?",
      "answer": "3600"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many words, with or without meaning, can be formed using all the letters of the word EQUATION at a time so that the vowels and consonants occur together?",
      "answer": "1440"
    },
    {
      "question": "A committee of 7 has to be formed from 9 boys and 4 girls. In how many ways can this be done when the committee consists of: (i) exactly 3 girls ? (ii) atleast 3 girls ? (iii) atmost 3 girls ?",
      "answer": "(i) 504 (ii) 588 (iii) 1632"
    },
    {
      "question": "If the different permutations of all the letter of the word EXAMINATION are listed as in a dictionary, how many words are there in this list before the first word starting with E ?",
      "answer": "907200"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many 6-digit numbers can be formed from the digits 0, 1, 3, 5, 7 and 9 which are divisible by 10 and no digit is repeated ?",
      "answer": "120"
    },
    {
      "question": "The English alphabet has 5 vowels and 21 consonants. How many words with two different vowels and 2 different consonants can be formed from the alphabet ?",
      "answer": "50400"
    },
    {
      "question": "In an examination, a question paper consists of 12 questions divided into two parts i.e., Part I and Part II, containing 5 and 7 questions, respectively. A student is required to attempt 8 questions in all, selecting at least 3 from each part. In how many ways can a student select the questions ?",
      "answer": "420"
    },
    {
      "question": "Determine the number of 5-card combinations out of a deck of 52 cards if each selection of 5 cards has exactly one king.",
      "answer": "4C1×48C4"
    },
    {
      "question": "It is required to seat 5 men and 4 women in a row so that the women occupy the even places. How many such arrangements are possible ?",
      "answer": "2880"
    },
    {
      "question": "From a class of 25 students, 10 are to be chosen for an excursion party. There are 3 students who decide that either all of them will join or none of them will join. In how many ways can the excursion party be chosen ?",
      "answer": "22C7+22C10"
    },
    {
      "question": "In how many ways can the letters of the word ASSASSINATION be arranged so that all the S's are together ?",
      "answer": "151200"
    }
  ]
}